Okay, so let us discuss a
few types and example values.
Maybe not exactly all the cases from the
last slide but similar ones that combine
base types: lists, tuples, in some mixed fashion.
Okay, let's start with the
type of lists of integer lists.
Okay, so this is a type.
What are some of its values?
And I will simply list this and talk through this,
maybe also some values and some non-values to
make clear what is going on here.
So, of course, you always have the empty
list. The empty list is a list of any type,
the empty list is both a list of integers,
but also a list of lists of integers.
The list which is not the empty
list but contains the empty list.
Yes, this is the kind of list that you get in
set theory where you have a singleton
set, which contains the empty set.
Then, the corresponding thing
in Haskell would be this,
the singleton list which contains one
element, which is the empty list.
This is something of the type
"list of list of integers".
It wouldn't be something of type list of integers,
because then the inner list doesn't make sense.
Okay, but this type that's
written there, it is okay.
Of course, these are somewhat
basic and trivial lists.
But let's also look at something like this.
This is, of course, also a list of integer lists.
Why?
Because this is an integer list, this is an integer
list and together we have a list of integer lists.
Okay, and of course, this could go on, right,
where both the inner and the outer lists
could have more values or more lists.
And what we can do is replace one of
the integers by something else, by True
or 'a' or whatever, right?
This would be wrong because then we would
violate the homogeneity of the lists.
Of course, it's also not
possible to have just this.
This is a list of integers, it is
not a list of lists of integers.
So, it is not a value of this type.
And likewise, of course, something like
this is not of correct type because
it is, again, not homogeneous.
We have here an integer, and here a
list of integers, these are not things
that can go together in one outer
list so this is also not okay.
Yes, so these are nested lists.
And of course, this can be
repeated for other types.
Okay, let's make an example of tuples and of
course, you could have pairs, and then on the pairs,
for example, we can project on the first and
second components with corresponding functions.
But we don't need to have
pairs, we can also have triples.
So, something like this.
And, as mentioned before, tuples
are always of a fixed length.
So, if I have a triple,
then it always has to have
three components, but they
might be of different types.
But of course, one tuple type, it's
fixed, what can go in which position?
So, for example, for this
type, some values would be this
where we have an integer here, then we have a
string, say "abc", then you have a Boolean value.
And of course, it could choose this, we could
change this to another integer, we could
put other strings here and we could put False
here and consider all the combinations, but what
we can't do is take, for example, the same three
components, but give them in a different order.
Even though this would be
the same three components,
it's not something of the given type,
because the order is not respected.
The types don't match the position.
Okay, and one further example.
So, let's mix.
For example, lists and pairs.
So, let's consider this type.
Here we have list type.
And what we have in the list
are pairs of, for example,
Bools and integers, let me make these brackets clear,
this is a round bracket and this is a square bracket.
Then what could be some values of that type?
So, the empty list, of
course, it's always possible.
So, of course, this means that the
empty list can have different types.
Unsurprisingly, because there's no element inside
that would predetermine some specific type.
And then, of course, the non-empty
lists now must contain pairs.
So, of course, this is not possible, right?
We can't have a list of the empty
list, and a type of lists of pairs.
But for example, you could have a singleton
list, which contains a pair of a true value
and the number 4, for example, or we could
have a list of more than one element, or
say the list of the pair of (False,
5), and (True, 4), and so on.
What we can't, of course, do is somehow switch
some components, yes, this would not be okay.
But if it respects the order, then we can get
further list elements here which are pairs.
Okay, and maybe one further example.
Let's say lists of pairs of
integers and lists of Bools.
So, let this be our type,
then what are some values?
Well, for example, it can
of course be the empty list,
but also the list which
contains a pair
of an integer number and a list of Bools,
which could, for example, be the empty list.
Yes, this would be okay.
Or the list which consists of a pair
which has 0 as its first component,
and then a non-singleton list like
neither empty nor singleton list,
let's say False and True combined in one list.
Yes, of course, this didn't
appear in the examples above.
Of course, lists are not sets.
So, I could have put False, False there,
for example, it would also have been
okay; or False, False, True, True.
So, these are lists.
And let me make just one more example here.
So, let's say a list which is neither empty nor
the singleton list, it's a list of two elements.
The first element is a pair of a natural number of
an integer and a list, let's say the empty list.
And the second pair is a pair with a number, say
2, and a list, which would be a list of Bools.
So, it could, for example, be the
singleton list containing True.
Okay, and of course, there are many more
example values for each of the types above.
These are just for illustration of how
these things are mixed and play together,
if you want to express more complex
structures than just plain or flat lists.